Eugene McCarthy presidential campaign speech files collection
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
Eugene McCarthy presidential campaign speech files collection
1967-1968
C0203
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
1.0 linear feet (2 boxes)
The Eugene McCarthy presidential campaign papers contain documents from six speech file "books" used by the campaign staff. The speeches span from October 1967 to July 1968 and include remarks he gave prior to his entry into the race for the Democratic nomination. Some of the speeches are from campaign stops in particular primary states, such as Nebraska, and the speeches generally document McCarthy's positions on the Vietnam War, the economy, and race relations.
McCarthy, Eugene J., 1916-2005
Acquisition Information
Donated by Hampton Brown in 2011.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged chronologically.
Scope and Content
The Eugene McCarthy presidential campaign papers contain documents from six speech file "books" used by the campaign staff. The speeches span from October 1967 to July 1968 and include remarks he gave prior to his entry into the race for the Democratic nomination. Some of the speeches are from campaign stops in particular primary states, such as Nebraska, and the speeches generally document McCarthy's positions on the Vietnam War, the economy, and race relations. Although most of the documents are speeches, there are also transcripts of debates, television appearances, and press conferences. The transcripts include an exchange between McCarthy and Robert Kennedy on ABC television, and another transcript documents McCarthy's appearance on the Tonight Show with Johnny Carson. A press conference transcript from June 14, 1968, is particularly notable since it appears to be the first press conference McCarthy held following the assassination of Robert Kennedy. The documents are all photocopies, but some of them contain handwritten edits that were also copied.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Existence and Location of Copies
Copies of these speeches can be found in the Eugene McCarthy papers at the University of Minnesota.
Historical Information
On November 30, 1967, Democratic Senator Eugene McCarthy of Minnesota announced his candidacy for President of the United States. He positioned himself as the anti-Vietnam War candidate to present a clear distinction between himself and the incumbent president, Lyndon Johnson. With the help of younger voters, particularly college students, McCarthy gathered enough support to challenge Johnson in the primaries, and on March 31, 1968, Johnson dropped out of the race rather than face a long nomination battle against McCarthy as well as Robert F. Kennedy. Following Johnson's exit, Vice-President Hubert Humphrey entered the race, and George McGovern joined the race after the assassination of Kennedy on June 5. McCarthy went on to lose the nomination at the Democratic convention in Chicago, and the Democratic nominee Hubert Humphrey lost in the general election to Richard M. Nixon. Hampton Brown, the collection donor, worked for the McCarthy campaign.
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds other collections United States politics and government in the 20th century.
Index Terms
Persons:
Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968.; McCarthy, Eugene J., 1916-2005.
Geographical Names:
United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.
Subjects:
Political campaigns--United States.; Presidential candidates.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Protest movements--United States.
Contents List
- Chronological Speech File Book I, October 4, 1967-January 26, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Folder 1 of 2.
- Chronological Speech File Book I, October 4, 1967-January 26, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Folder 2 of 2.
- Chronological Speech File Book A, January 26-April 1, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Folder 1 of 3.
- Chronological Speech File Book A, January 26-April 1, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Folder 2 of 3.
- Chronological Speech File Book A, January 26-April 1, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Folder 3 of 3.
- Chronological Speech File for Indiana and Nebraska Book B, April 1-May 14, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Chronological Speech File for Indiana and Nebraska Book B, April 1-May 14, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Chronological Speech File for Indiana and Nebraska Book B, April 1-May 14, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Chronological Speech File for Oregon and California Book C, May 14-June 4, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Chronological Speech File for Oregon and California Book C, May 14-June 4, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Chronological Speech File for New York Book D, June 14-July 4, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Chronological Speech File Research Dept., July 5-July 31, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Chronological Speech File Research Dept., July 5-July 31, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)